Agenda

Présentation de la PLS par Adama

Présentation du Random Forest par Trang

Discussions autour des présentations

PLS

PPT de la présentation : 2014-12-18_pls_-_adama.pptx

Random Forest

PPT de la présentation :

Idées scientifiques et de travail

Il serait intéressant de fixer les idées qui on pu naître suite à la présentation. J'y ai mis quelques idées de chaucun notées durant et après la réunion. Merci d'y apporter plus détails.

Pierre/Trang Faire un Benchmark de plusieurs méthodes du random forest sur le centre de calcul

Lilia Combiner le Random Forest à PLS en tirant partie des avantages de chacun. E.g. PLS pour factoriser et simplifier l'espace des varaibles, RF pour la construction du modèle final en vue de la simulation et la prédiction.

Adama Un point intéressant du Random Forest dans le cadre des algorithmes d'apprentissage est sa simplicitité de construction. La construction itérative des arbres de décisions en séparant de manière naturelle l'espace des variables des plus informatives aux moins informatives, chaque neud de séparation étant associé à une règle de décision (e.g. IF X > k THEN [ IF B > m THEN […] ], ELSE […]). Il serait donc intéressant d'explorer la possibilité du RF (ou même des algortihmes basés sur ces arbres de décision) pour l'apprentissge naturelle et la construction de nos propres modèles de prédiction pour l'analyse fonctionnelle. En analyse fonctionnelle des pathways, le rule-based et agent-based modelling http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rule-based_modeling, http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Agent-based_model_in_biology sont à cet effet des outils qui permettent de modéliser un ensemble d'interactions moléculaires à partir de règles. On peut donc imaginer le RF comme un outil qui permettrait de classer l'information à partir des données biologiques (conditionnées sur un endpoint biologique à prédire) afin de construire en base de données une série de modèles qui seront utilisées pour faire de la prédiction. Par expérience, la possibilité de représenter les modèles RF sous forme d'arbre de décision les rend aussi biologically human-readable, ce qui est un atout majeur quand on doit presenter un modèles mathématiques à des biologistes. E.g. Savoir que IF <Gene_A_actif> THEN <Phenotype_B> est bien plus naturel comme représentation que <Phenotype_B> = K * <Level_Gene_A> ou <Phentype_B> = f(<Level_Gene_A>), f étant une fonction non linéaire comme c'est le cas avec les méthodes de régression linéaires/non-linéaires (e.g. K-PLS). Questions pour Trang: Suposons qu'on a un modèle A1 construit sur une jeu de données D1. Suppsons qu'une nouvelle données D2 arrive. Est-il possible de mettre à jour A1 en intégrant simplement la nouvelle données D2 sans avoir à recalculer tout le modèle avec [D1, D2] ?

Lilia, j'ai noté “dans ma tête” il y a quelques semaines, qu'à une conférence tu avais vu des gens parler du rule-based modelling (je ne sais si tu t'en souviens ?). Penses-tu que tu pourais les inviter ou d'avoir accès à leurs travaux ? Si tu veux, il serait intéressant que tu mette aussi les idées que tu en avais tirées en fonction de leurs travaux… si tu a un CR cette conf il serait le bienvenu [Adama].

Points à améliorer/supprimer/conserver pour les prochaines présentation

Au vu du large spectre de compétences bioinfo, il serait intéressant les points sur lesquels chacun souhaite plus d'approndissement pour les prochaine présentations par exemple. Par exemple, Pierre avait souhaité plus de graphiques sur la PLS pour rendre la méthode plus concrète.

ToDo

Adama : Prévoir une présentation avec le logiciel SIMCA avec illustration de la PLS et l'O-PLS

Pierre : Voir avec l'utec6 de la possibilité de mettre en place le benchmark Random Forest

Lilia/Trang/Adama + autres ? Réfléchir à pipeline d'analyse où on pourrait combiner PSL, O-PLS (filtrage, analyse de la strucutre des données : étape mi-manuelle/mi-automatique) + RF (construction de modèles finaux à base d'arbres de décision)

Adama/Lilia ? : Inviter des personnes (chercheurs) extérieurs pour nous faire par de leur expérimences sur le Rule-Based et Agent-Based modelling. Adama a qq adresses pour ça, notamment une doctorante de l'INRIA Rocquencourt et un post-doc de L'ENS Cachan qu'on pourrait faire venir. Lilia, j'ai noté il y a quelques semaines, qu'à une conférence tu avais vu des gens parler du rule-based modelling (je ne sais si tu t'en souviens ?). Penses-tu que tu pourais les inviter ou d'avoir accès à leurs travaux ?

[Nicolas] Gardez en tête que les thèmes du rule-based et de l'agent based modelling sont des thèmes développés chez des partenaires potentiels et qui pourraient avoir un intérêt dans le diagnostic

[Adama] Peux-tu préciser de quels partenaires il s’agit car c’est intéressant et il serait mieux peut-être bien d’approfondir ces aspects directement avec eux dans ce cas. Merci d’avance.

Install and configure Hortonworks sandbox

Full official tutorial can be found https://www.cloudera.com/tutorials/learning-the-ropes-of-the-hdp-sandbox.html

1.Deploy Hortonworks sandbox

Hortonworks sandbox provides three ways to deploy it:

vmware image

virtual box image

docker file

To deploy the vmware and virtual box image, it's quite easy, just create a vm based on the image. Then follow the configuration instruction which we will show in the next section.

Run docker file in a docker container, you will need more works

1.1 Deploy Hortonworks in a docker container

Install and run docker (See Part1 : Orientation and setup for docker installation)

Downlaod the docker file for HDP (https://www.cloudera.com/downloads/hortonworks-sandbox/hdp.html?utm_source=mktg-tutorial)

Unzip the file, it should contain one file docker-deploy-hdp30.sh and a directory assets.

Run sh docker-deploy-hdp30.sh

Check the docker process docker ps

Manage the HDP docker process

# When you want to stop/shutdown your HDP sandbox, run the following commands:
docker stop sandbox-hdp
docker stop sandbox-proxy

# When you want to re-start your sandbox, run the following commands:
docker start sandbox-hdp
docker start sandbox-proxy

# If you want to remove sandbox containers. A container is an instance of the Sandbox image. You must stop 
# container dependencies before removing it. Issue the following commands:
docker stop sandbox-hdp
docker stop sandbox-proxy
docker rm sandbox-hdp
docker rm sandbox-proxy

# If you want to remove the HDP Sandbox image, issue the following command after stopping and removing the containers:
docker rmi hortonworks/sandbox-hdp:{release}

2. Configure sandbox VM/Container

2.1 Set up IP hostname mapping in your host machine

When you open your sandbox services in your host machine browsers, based on your installation, the IP address could be different.

Docker: IP Address = 127.0.0.1

VirtualBox: IP Address = 127.0.0.1

VMWare: IP Address = 192.168.x.x

# In linux
# You need to modify the IP address accordingly
echo '<IP> sandbox-hdp.hortonworks.com sandbox-hdf.hortonworks.com' | sudo tee -a /etc/hosts

# In mac
echo '{IP-Address} sandbox-hdp.hortonworks.com sandbox-hdf.hortonworks.com' | sudo tee -a /private/etc/hosts

# In windows
# 1. Run Notepad as administrator.
# 2. Open hosts file located in: c:\Windows\System32\drivers\etc\hosts
# 3. Add {IP-Address} localhost sandbox-hdp.hortonworks.com sandbox-hdf.hortonworks.com
# 4. Save the file

2.2 Connect to your VM

# The sandbox does not use the port 22 for ssh, it uses 2222 instead
ssh root@sandbox-hdp.hortonworks.com -p 2222

# If you did not do the IP hostname mapping step, you need to replace the hostname by the IP address
# For the first connection, the password: **hadoop**, you need to modify it.

2.3 File transfer between sandbox and host machine

# Send file from host to sandbox
scp -P 2222 /tmp/toto.txt root@sandbox-hdp.hortonworks.com:/home/pliu/.

# Send file from sandbox to host
scp -P 2222 root@sandbox-hdp.hortonworks.com:<sandbox_directory_file> <local_directory_file>

2.4 Reset ambari admin password

Ambari Dashboard runs on port: 8080. For example, http://sandbox-hdp.hortonworks.com:8080. Or Replace url by the real ip address. (e.g. http://192.168.184.129:8080/#/main/dashboard ). You can use the following login to access the page:

login | pwd | role | Tool access
maria_dev | maria_dev | Spark and SQL Developer | Hive, Zeppelin, MapReduce/Tez/Spark, Pig, Solr, HBase/Phoenix, Sqoop, NiFi, Storm, Kafka, Flume
raj_ops | raj_ops | Hadoop Warehouse Operator | Hive/Tez, Ranger, Falcon, Knox, Sqoop, Oozie, Flume, Zookeeper
holger_gov | holger_gov | Data Steward | Atlas
amy_ds | amy_ds | Data Scientist | Spark, Hive, R, Python, Scala

If you want to login as admin, you need to initiate the admin password

# You need to ssh into the sandbox vm and type the following command
$ ambari-admin-password-reset 

2.5 Change Atlas password

# Change admin password
# 1. Open config GUI of atlas via ambari. 
# 2. In clause advanced atlas-env, you can change the admin password. 

# If you want to add a new user, you need to go to your sandbox vm 
# 1. Generate the hash of your password
$ echo -n "Password" | sha256sum
# 2. Open file /etc/atlas/conf/users-credentials.properties with vim
$ vim /etc/atlas/conf/users-credentials.properties
# 3. add a line like this: pliu=ROLE_ADMIN::b012da22fa1439aacbe02971d7321e56a82ad75da84bc6e27358f3593e5b9b24 
in the file.
# 4. Restart the atlas service to make it available.

2.6 change mysql server root password

Hortonworks sandbox uses a mysql server to store the configuration infomation, hive metastore, etc. In some version the password for root is hadoop. In some version, the password is empty.

But if you can't login with mysql -u root -p, you need to follow the following instructions (Reset root password for MySql or MariaDB) to reset the root password.

3. Common problems

3.1 Docker container sandbox-proxy can't start

Command: Docker start sandbox-proxy Error: Error response from daemon: driver failed programming external connectivity on endpoint sandbox-proxy (8f1dc79b789604e45f88cb15045d8dfc6d8f11f9d195ccd2765a03758759ea94): (iptables failed: iptables –wait -t nat -A DOCKER -p tcp -d 0/0 –dport 61888 -j DNAT –to-destination 172.18.0.3:61888 ! -i br-7e3d72e7f4ac: iptables: No chain/target/match by that name.

Solution: To correct this, you need to restart docker daemon Systemctl restart docker

3.2 Ambari can't start the hdp services

Command: Ambari start all services Error: Mysqld daemon can't start, raise error 2019-09-20T14:09:43.429317Z 0 [ERROR] InnoDB: Ignoring the redo log due to missing MLOG_CHECKPOINT between the checkpoint 19668090 and the end 19669084. 2019-09-20T14:09:43.429326Z 0 [ERROR] InnoDB: Plugin initialization aborted with error Generic error 2019-09-20T14:09:44.029878Z 0 [ERROR] Plugin 'InnoDB' init function returned error. 2019-09-20T14:09:44.029892Z 0 [ERROR] Plugin 'InnoDB' registration as a STORAGE ENGINE failed.

Solution: To correct this, you need to clean the InnoDB log file rm -rf /var/lib/mysql/ib_logfile

3.3 Atlas add classification permission denied

Command: Add classification/term, etc. Error: Permission denied

Solution: Atlas needs to write in HBASE, In a cluster managed by ambari, we use Knox (Provides a single point of authentication and access for Apache Hadoop services in a cluster) to make the authentication and access control possible. So before running Atlas, start Knox, HBase, Solr first.

3.4 Load hdfs data into hive table pemission deny

Command: hive load data to hive table Error: Permission denied

Solution: When load data into hive table, hive will move the data from the hdfs source location to hive data warehouse (also a hdfs path). The user who launch this command must make sure he has the right to write in both locations.

Ansible Install and configuration

1. Install ansible on centos 7/8

# on centos 8, yum will install ansible 2.9 by default
sudo yum install ansible

# You can check your ansible version 
ansible --version

2. Configuration

The full document on ansible configuration:

https://docs.ansible.com/ansible/latest/installation_guide/intro_configuration.html#getting-the-latest-configuration

2.1 Hosts configuration

Ansible works against multiple managed nodes or “hosts” in your infrastructure at the same time. We need to specify a list or group of lists of servers (a.k.a inventory), to indicate which servers you want Ansible to run against.

The default location for specify this inventory is a file /etc/ansible/hosts.

2.1.1 Customize inventory files

You can specify a different inventory file at the command line using the -i <path> option. If you have multiple inventory files, you can use -i as many time as you want. For example, if you have two files a,b you can use the following commmand

ansible-playbook get_logs.yml -i a -i b

The inventory file can be in INI or YMAL. For example, a basic INI inventory (etc/ansible/hosts) might look like this:

cent8_sql01.pengfei.org

[udl_datalake]
lin[01:06].udl.org


[cluster_manager]
lin01.udl.org

[service_node]
lin02.udl.org
lin03.udl.org
159.84.108.202

[worker_node]
159.84.108.201
159.84.108.200

Default groups

There are two default groups:

all: It contains every host in the inventory

ungrouped. It contains all hosts that don’t have another group aside from all. For example, in the above inventory, the ungrouped group has one host which is cent8_sql01.pengfei.org.

Every host will always belong to at least 2 groups (all and ungrouped or all and some other group). Though all and ungrouped are always present, they can be implicit and not appear in group listings like group_names.

We can also write an inventory in YAML format

all:
  hosts:
    cent8_sql01.pengfei.org:
  udl_datalake:
    hosts: 
      lin[01:06].udl.org:
  cluster_manager:  
    hosts:
      lin01.udl.org:
  service_node:
    hosts:
      lin02.udl.org:
      lin03.udl.org:
      159.84.108.202:
  worker_node:
    hosts:
      159.84.108.201:
      159.84.108.200:

There are some important points:

The hosts can be an URL or an IP address.

A host can be in multiple groups.

If you have many servers which have the same pattern you can use a range like www[01:50].example.com to specify them all. It also works for letters db-[a:f].example.com.

2.1.2 Group variables

You can also set variables in the inventory file

lin01.udl.org http_port=80 maxRequestsPerChild=808
lin02.udl.org http_port=303 maxRequestsPerChild=909
<code>

If all hosts in a group share a variable value, you can apply that variable to an entire group at once. In INI:

<code>
[udl_datalake]
host1
host2

[udl_datalake:vars]
ntp_server=ntp.udl.org
proxy=proxy.udl.org

2.1.3 Host group hierarchy

We can use keyword children to group groups of hosts.

[beijing]
host1
host2

[shanghai]
host2
host3

[southeast:children]
beijing
shanghai

[southeast:vars]
some_server=foo.southeast.example.com
halon_system_timeout=30
self_destruct_countdown=60
escape_pods=2

[china:children]
southeast
northeast
southwest
northwest

Here, group china contains all servers of the southeast, …, northwest region, and southeast region contains all servers of beijing and shanghai.

The variables in vars will apply to all servers of the southeast region.

3. Ansible playbook Content Organization

The Content organization in ansible playbook is very important. You can find all best practices in the following link

https://docs.ansible.com/ansible/latest/user_guide/playbooks_best_practices.html

I prefer to organize my playbook in the following way.

inventories/
   production/
      hosts               # inventory file for production servers
      group_vars/
         group1.yml       # here we assign variables to particular groups
         group2.yml
      host_vars/
         hostname1.yml    # here we assign variables to particular systems
         hostname2.yml

   staging/
      hosts               # inventory file for staging environment
      group_vars/
         group1.yml       # here we assign variables to particular groups
         group2.yml
      host_vars/
         stagehost1.yml   # here we assign variables to particular systems
         stagehost2.yml

library/                  # if any custom modules, put them here (optional)
module_utils/             # if any custom module_utils to support modules, put them here (optional)
filter_plugins/           # if any custom filter plugins, put them here (optional)

site.yml                  # master playbook
webservers.yml            # playbook for webserver tier
dbservers.yml             # playbook for dbserver tier

roles/
    common/               # this hierarchy represents a "role"
        tasks/            #
            main.yml      #  <-- tasks file can include smaller files if warranted
        handlers/         #
            main.yml      #  <-- handlers file
        templates/        #  <-- files for use with the template resource
            ntp.conf.j2   #  <------- templates end in .j2
        files/            #
            bar.txt       #  <-- files for use with the copy resource
            foo.sh        #  <-- script files for use with the script resource
        vars/             #
            main.yml      #  <-- variables associated with this role
        defaults/         #
            main.yml      #  <-- default lower priority variables for this role
        meta/             #
            main.yml      #  <-- role dependencies
        library/          # roles can also include custom modules
        module_utils/     # roles can also include custom module_utils
        lookup_plugins/   # or other types of plugins, like lookup in this case

    webtier/              # same kind of structure as "common" was above, done for the webtier role
    monitoring/           # ""
    fooapp/               # ""

3.1 How variables are merged

By default, variables are merged/flattened to the specific host before a play is run. This keeps Ansible focused on the Host and Task, so groups don’t really survive outside of inventory and host matching. By default, Ansible overwrites variables including the ones defined for a group and/or host (see https://docs.ansible.com/ansible/latest/reference_appendices/config.html#default-hash-behaviour). The order/precedence is (from lowest to highest):

all group (because it is the ‘parent’ of all other groups)

parent group

child group

host

4. Run playbook with options

# Run your playbook with default inventory
ansible-playbook site.yml

# Run with customize inventory
ansible-playbook -i datalake_inventory site.yml

You can override the default variables defines in the playbook. Suppose in your playbook, you have two variables (e.g. user_name and user_pwd). You can overwrite them with the following command

ansible-playbook site.yml –extra-vars "user_name=toto user_pwd=changeMe"

Before you run the playbook on the server, you may want to test which hosts and which task the playbook will run on. You can use the following options.

ansible-playbook --list-hosts --list-tasks site.yml

The full option explanation page is here https://docs.ansible.com/ansible/latest/cli/ansible-playbook.html

Introduction

TensorFlow is an open-source machine learning software built by Google to train neural networks. TensorFlow's neural networks are expressed in the form of stateful dataflow graphs. Each node in the graph represents the operations performed by neural networks on multi-dimensional arrays. These multi-dimensional arrays are commonly known as “tensors”, hence the name TensorFlow.

TensorFlow is a deep learning software system. TensorFlow works well for information retrieval, as demonstrated by Google in how they do search ranking in their machine-learning artificial intelligence system, RankBrain. TensorFlow can perform image recognition, as shown in Google's Inception, as well as human language audio recognition. It's also useful in solving other problems not specific to machine learning, such as partial differential equations.

The TensorFlow architecture allows for deployment on multiple CPUs or GPUs within a desktop, server or mobile device. There are also extensions for integration with CUDA, a parallel computing platform from Nvidia. This gives users who are deploying on a GPU direct access to the virtual instruction set and other elements of the GPU that are necessary for parallel computational tasks.

In this tutorial, you'll install TensorFlow's “CPU support only” version. This installation is ideal for people looking to install and use TensorFlow, but who don't have an Nvidia graphics card or don't need to run performance-critical applications.

You can install TensorFlow several ways. Each method has a different use case and development environment:

Install keras with tensorflow as backend

I strongly recommand you to use virtual env to install python dev environment.

Follow this tutorial to build a virtuel env Install python 3 on centos 7 and virtual env

Install tensorflow

I suppose you already have a virtual env which runs on python 3.6

# go to your virtual env and activate it
source my_venv/bin/activate

# update your pip first
pip install --upgrade pip

# install tensorflow
pip install --upgrade tensorflow

Install keras

#install dependencies first
pip install numpy scipy
pip install scikit-learn
pip install pillow
pip install h5py

# install keras 

pip install keras

After the installation of keras, you should find a keras config file keras.json in

vim ~/.keras/keras.json

# you should see the following line
{
    "floatx": "float32",
    "epsilon": 1e-07,
    "backend": "tensorflow",
    "image_data_format": "channels_last"
}

Specifically, you’ll want to ensure that image_data_format is set to “channels_last” (indicating that the TensorFlow image dimension ordering is used rather than “channels_first” for Theano).

You’ll also want to ensure that the backend is properly set to tensorflow (rather than theano ). Again, both of these requirements should be satisfied by the default Keras configuration but it doesn’t hurt to double check.

A quick note on image_data_format You might be wondering what exactly image_data_format controls.

Using TensorFlow, images are represented as NumPy arrays with the shape (height, width, depth), where the depth is the number of channels in the image.

However, if you are using Theano, images are instead assumed to be represented as (depth, height, width).

This little nuance is the source of a lot of headaches when using Keras (and a lot of if statments looking for these particular configurations).

Debugging

If you are getting strange results when using Keras (or an error message related to the shape of a given tensor) you should:

Check your backend. Ensure your image dimension ordering matches your backend.

Test your Keras+tensorFlow

$ python
Python 3.6.5 (default, Apr 10 2018, 17:08:37) 
[GCC 4.8.5 20150623 (Red Hat 4.8.5-16)] on linux
Type "help", "copyright", "credits" or "license" for more information.
>>> import keras
Using TensorFlow backend.
>>> 

If you see the above lines, we cloud say our keras tensorflow installation is done.

What's next

You can follow this tutorial to do your first neural network with keras

Install anaconda

Introduction

Anaconda is the most popular python data science and machine learning platform, used for large-scale data processing, predictive analytics, and scientific computing. Anaconda distribution ships with more than 1,000 data packages, the conda command-line tool and with a desktop graphical user interface called Anaconda Navigator.

Anaconda vs Pip

Having been involved in the python world for so long, we are all aware of pip, easy_install, and virtualenv, but these tools did not meet all of our specific requirements. The main problem is that they are focused around Python, neglecting non-Python library dependencies, such as HDF5, MKL, LLVM, etc., which do not have a setup.py in their source code and also do not install files into Python’s site-packages directory.

So Conda is a packaging tool and installer that aims to do more than what pip does; handle library dependencies outside of the Python packages as well as the Python packages themselves. Conda also creates a virtual environment, like virtualenv does.

Because Conda introduces a new packaging format, you cannot use pip and Conda interchangeably; pip cannot install the Conda package format. You can use the two tools side by side (by installing pip with conda install pip) but they do not interoperate either.

Step1. Get the conda installer

You can get all available conda version at https://www.anaconda.com/distribution/#download-section. In this tutorial we choose the current latest version Anaconda3-2018.12. The following code will download the installer

cd /tmp
curl -O https://repo.anaconda.com/archive/Anaconda3-2018.12-Linux-x86_64.sh

# check the script checksum
sha256sum Anaconda3-2018.12-Linux-x86_64.sh 
1019d0857e5865f8a6861eaf15bfe535b87e92b72ce4f531000dc672be7fce00  Anaconda3-2018.12-Linux-x86_64.sh

# compare the above checksums with the checksum of the anaconda web site 

Step2. Run the anaconda installer

Before you run the installer, you need to know, anaconda will download and install a python 3.7.0 which will you overwrite all your python3.7 installation.

Anaconda installer needs some system dependencies to do the install, install the following dependencies

yum install -y bzip2 

# run the installer, it's not recommended to run with sudo. Choose the user who wishes to install conda 
sh Anaconda3-2018.12-Linux-x86_64.sh

# you will be prompted with a series of questions. based on your needs, answer yes or no.
Installation finished.

Do you wish the installer to initialize Anaconda3
in your /home/linuxize/.bashrc ? [yes|no]

# I recommend you to enter yes

The installer will also ask you whether you would like to download and install Visual Studio Code. You can find more information about Visual Studio on the website (https://code.visualstudio.com/). If you want to install Visual Studio Code type yes otherwise type no.

To activate the Anaconda installation load the new PATH environment variable which was added by the Anaconda installer into the current shell session with the following command:

source ~/.bashrc

Step3. Verify the conda installation

conda info

Step4. Updating Anaconda

# Updating the Anaconda is a pretty straight forward process, first update the conda tool with:
conda update anaconda

# Once conda is updated, proceed with the Anaconda update:
conda update anaconda

You should regularly update your Anaconda installation.

Deleting Anaconda

Step1. Remove the Anaconda install directory

# Find your anaconda installation path
rm -rf /path/to/anaconda3

Step2. Edit your ~/.bashrc

To remove conda from your path, you need to delete the lines which anaconda added, for example in my .bashrc I have the following line

# added by Anaconda3 5.3.1 installer
# >>> conda init >>>
# !! Contents within this block are managed by 'conda init' !!
__conda_setup="$(CONDA_REPORT_ERRORS=false '/home/linuxize/anaconda3/bin/conda' shell.bash hook 2> /dev/null)"
if [ $? -eq 0 ]; then
    \eval "$__conda_setup"
else
    if [ -f "/home/linuxize/anaconda3/etc/profile.d/conda.sh" ]; then
        . "/home/linuxize/anaconda3/etc/profile.d/conda.sh"
        CONDA_CHANGEPS1=false conda activate base
    else
        \export PATH="/home/linuxize/anaconda3/bin:$PATH"
    fi
fi
unset __conda_setup
# <<< conda init <<<

Delete them.

Step3. Remove the hidden files

The following command will remove the hidden files and folders that have been created by Anaconda in your user home directory:

rm -rf ~/.condarc ~/.conda ~/.continuum

DataBase view

A database view is a searchable object in a database that is defined by a query. Though a view doesn’t store data, some refer to a views as “virtual tables,” you can query a view like you can a table. A view can combine data from two or more table, using joins, and also just contain a subset of information. This makes them convenient to abstract, or hide, complicated queries.

How to Create and Use a Database View

A view is created from a query using the CREATE VIEW command. In the example below we are creating a PopularBooks view based of a query which selects all Books that have the IsPopular field checked. The Query is colored in Blue.

CREATE VIEW PopularBooks AS
SELECT ISBN, Title, Author, PublishDate
FROM Books
WHERE IsPopular = 1

Once a view is created you can used then as you would any table in a SELECT statement. For example, to list all the popular book titles ordered by author you could write:

SELECT Author, Title
FROM PopularBooks
ORDER BY Author

Benefits of a Database View

There are many benefits to using views. Listed below are some of the one that come to mind:

Enforce Business Rules Use views to define business rules, such as when an items is active, or what is meant by “popular.” By placing complicated or misunderstood business logic into the view, you can be sure to present a unified portrayal of the data. This increases use and quality.

Consistency Simplify complicated query logic and calculations by hiding it behind the view’s definition. Once defined they calculations are reference from the view rather than being restated in separate queries. This makes for less mistakes and easier maintenance of code.

Security Restrict access to a table, yet allow users to access non-confidential data via views. For example, you can restrict access to the employee table, that contains social security numbers, but allow access to a view containing name and phone number.

Simplicity Databases with many tables possess complex relationships, which can be difficult to navigate if you aren’t comfortable using Joins. Use views to provide a “flattened” view of the database for reporting or ad-hoc queries.

Space Views take up very little space, as the data is stored once in the source table. Some DBMS all you to create an index on a view, so in some cases views do take up more space than the definition.

Disadvantages of Views

Performance What may seem like a simple query against a view could turn out to be a hugely complex job for the database engine. That is because each time a view is referenced, the query used to define it, is rerun.

Modifications Not all views support INSERT, UPDATE, or DELETE operations. In general, in order to support these operations, the primary key and required fields must be present in the view. Complex multi-table views are generally read only.

GNU Bazaar

GNU Bazaar, abrégé bzr, est un outil de versionnement qui permet de garder une trace de toutes les modifications apportées à un ensemble de fichiers. Ce genre d'outils est particulièrement utilisé en informatique pour le développement collaboratif, mais il peut être utilisé pour n'importe quel type de document. GNU Bazaar est loin d'être le seul, mais il a été choisi pour des raisons précises.

Il existe plusieurs clients, graphiques ou en ligne de commande, sous GNU/Linux et Windows. Une fois installés, ils permettent d'effectuer les mêmes opérations assez facilement. Les concepts de base importants à saisir seront illustrés en utilisant le client en ligne de commande disponible sous tous les systèmes GNU.

La version pour Windows inclus, en plus de bazaar lui-même, les extensions pour l'explorateur de fichiers et l'outil bazaar explorer.

Introduction aux concepts de base

La première chose à faire est de se présenter auprès de bazaar. En effet, chaque version (aussi appelée révision) est attribuée à un auteur.

  $ bzr whoami "Tanguy LE CARROUR <tanguy.lecarrour@bioaster.org>"

On peut dès lors créer un dossier dans lequel on travaillera. Sauf exception, tous les fichiers et sous dossiers seront versionnés.

  $ mkdir mon_projet && cd mon_projet
  $ bzr init

Un dossier initialisé est aussi appelé une branche. La notion de branche sera abordée un peu plus tard.

On peut maintenant créer des fichiers et les ajouter à la liste des fichiers suivis par bazaar.

  $ touch mon_fichier.txt
  $ bzr add mon_fichier.txt

On peut maintenant enregistrer (commit) la première version du travail.

  $ bzr ci -m "Ajout d'un nouveau fichier au projet."

Par défaut, la commande commit (abrégée en ci) enregistre les modifications de tous les fichiers surveillés. Les noms de fichier peuvent être passés en argument pour n'enregistrer que certains d'en eux. Pour voir les fichiers modifiés pouvant être enregistrés, il suffit d'utiliser la commande bzr status.

On peut voir toutes les modifications enregistrées dans l'historique.

  $ bzr log
  ---------
  revno: 1
  commiter: Tanguy LE CARROUR <tanguy.lecarrour@bioaster.org>
  timestamp: Tue 2014-05-06 15:16:04 +0100
  message:
    Ajout d'un nouveau fichier au projet.

Si au lieu d'enregistrer les modifications on veut les annuler, il suffit d'utiliser la commande revert.

  $ vim mon_fichier.txt
  $ bzr st
  modified:
    mon_fichier.txt
  $ bzr revert mon_fichier.txt

Sans rentrer dans les détails du travail collaboratif sur un projet tout de suite, on peut présenter la commande branch qui permet, associée à une connexion SSH, de sauvegarder son travail sur un serveur distant.

  # Commande pour créer une branche, à utiliser uniquement si le projet n'existe pas
  $ bzr branch . bzr+ssh://mon.serveur.fr/~tanguy/repo/mon_projet
  # Commande à exécuter si la branche existe déjà 
  $ bzr push bzr+ssh://mon.serveur.fr/~tanguy/repo/mon_projet

Pour aller plus loin...

Pour mieux comprendre les concepts et les commandes abordés, on pourra se référer à la page traitant du travail collaboratif sur un projet et à la documentation officielle.

Certains concepts nécessitent des pages dédiées :

bonnes pratiques de fusion de branches

utilisation avancée

Le data management à BIOASTER

Les UTEC stores à BIOASTER 1

A, compléter

Les UTEC store sont créés sur la baie EMC de BIOASTER1 et montés sur les station de pilotage des équipements (montage SMB/NFS/CIFS?). Les fichiers générés par les appareils peuvent donc être directement copiés sur la baie.

A ce jour, les UTEC sotre ne sont pas sauvegardés !

Les UTEC store sont monté sur la VM de data management de BIOASTER1. De cette façon, l'UTEC6 pourra automatiser le transfert vers le CCIN2P3 (quand?). Les données des UTEC stores seront copiées dans /sps/bioaster/UTECstore/ (suggestion de NS)

OwnCloud

Actuellement

OwnCloud est un service Web d'échange et de partage de petits fichiers (<500 Mo). Il est accessible depuis l'URL https://ccbioappl04.in2p3.fr/owncloud/. Pour l'instant, OwnCloud possède sa propre base (SQLite) d'utilisateurs et stocke les données sur la baire EMC du CCIN2P3. Les données doivent être sauvegardées/copiées à la mano sur GPFS. Les groupes d'utilisateurs sont créés selon les directives de l'AQ stockées dans un fichier Excel. Ces directives dépendent des projets et du P.M.O.

OwnCloud2

Une migration vers OwnCloud2 se prépare afin que le service OwnCloud écrive directement les données sur GPFS. Depuis GPFS, les fichiers seront rendu accessible par des montages NFS sur les VM d'OpenStack du de VMware au CCIN2P3.

Tâche | Quoi? | Qui? | Avancement / Action
1 | Créer une VM OwnCloud 2 avec Apache et OwnCloud | TCL+AB |
2 | Créer un compte de data management qui écrira sur GPFS | NS | Compte créé
3 | Paramétrer OwnCloud et Apache pour qu'il utilise le compte générique | TLC+AB |
4 | Ansibeuliser le service | TCL+AB |
5 | Migrer la base de données SQLite ver pgSQL | AC+TLC |
6 | Créer un script pour migrer les données actuelle de la baie EMC vers GPFS | AC+TLC |
7 | Tester le script | AC+TLC+AB |
8 | Définir un nouveau DNS | AC+TLC+AB | owncloud.bioaster.org
9 | prévenir les utilisateur du changement et de l'arrêt de service | AC |
10 | Récupérer l'IP d'OwnCloud | AB |
11 | Arrêter OwnCloud et migrer | AB+AC+TLC |
12 | Démarrer OwnCloud2 et lui assigner l'IP et un nouveau DNS | AB |

Points bloquants identifiés :

Les données appartiendront à biodata du groupe bioaster, et plus à des personnes physiques.

Lors du montage NFS sur les VM GNU/Linux, il faudra forcer le UID/GID dans la VM pour que l'écriture se fasse au nom de biodata.

Il n'y a pas d'interface SMB pour permettre le montage de GPFS sous Windows.

Point 1 : Il semble que l'on puisse donner n'importe quel UID/GID à GPFS, même si l'utilisateur n'a pas de compte CCIN2P3. Ca permettrait de garder le nom de l'utilisateur et de gérer les droits avec des groupes propres au labo bioaster (tel que défini par le CCIN2P3). En revanche, il faut déterminer si OwnCloud peut écrire en utilisant plusieurs UID/GID.

Point 2 : A priori, c'est possible et ça a été testé par AB. On peut forcer n'importe quel UID/GID dans la VM.

Point 3 : Il faut voir avec le CC s'il peuvent nous fournir une interface SMB à GPFS (AB s'en charge?)